This דף *Daf* is צדי דלת *Tzadi Daled* 94 and we pick
up on the משנה Mishna, *Mishna* at the bottom of צדי גימל
עמוד בית *Tzadi Gimmel Amud Bais*. No brilliant new explanations of this
משנה Mishna *Mishna*
unfortunately. Somebody'll have to write another paper 2,000 years from now or
something. Anyway, all right. מי שהיה נשוי ארבע נשים *Mi shehaya nasuy
arba nashim*. As three wives weren't enough, married to four wives. Apparently
this is a Muslim allowed to marry up to four wives, you
know that? Their maximum is four because Mohammed married four wives. I'll
tell you later about a store a joke I told to some
Muslim women or whatever about that. Okay, מי שהיה *Mi shehaya* got
your interest. Then it gets better. Yeah, I told you that joke.
מי שהיה נשוי ארבע נשים ומת *Mi shehaya nasuy arba nashim umes*.
Married to four women and then he died. הראשונה קודמת לשניה ושניה
לשלישית *Harishona kodemes lashniya
veshniya lashlishis*. Yeah, that's what that's what David meant. ושלישית לרביעית *Veshlishis
leriviis*. הראשונה *Harishona*. Okay. So, who collects the estate first? The last
משנה Mishna *Mishna* was really fun, but it was a complete hypothetical
because it had him married to all three women at the exact
at that he initially married them on the exact same date. So
therefore their liens were all simultaneous. This is a normal story, normal
of a man with four wives, where their liens where he married
them one after the other and their liens are sequential. So therefore
the rule is that the one with the earlier lien that he
married first has the first right to the property. הראשונה קודמת לשניה
ושניה לשלישית ושלישית לרביעית *Harishona kodemes lashniya veshniya lashlishis veshlishis leriviis*. One
comes before two, two before three, three before four. Now, when one
is coming to take the property and to exercise her liens and
collect, והראשונה נשבעת לשניה *Veharishona nishbaas lashniya*. She has to make an
oath to the second one. Now, the general rule is that somebody
who is coming to collect from the orphans, whether it is a
creditor or whether it is the widow, has to make an oath
to them. And the oath basically is that none of the debt
has already been paid off. Because the orphans, if the guy was
alive and it was paid off, he would make that claim and
they would fight it out, but the orphans might not know whether
the father had paid up the claim. Now we're going to see
in the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* that that might be limited to a
case of orphans who are minors who are not in a position
to really
look into their father's papers and to make that claim for themselves.
And therefore if there
are orphans that are adults, then let them make that claim, let
them check out the father's papers. Why should that be the responsibility
of the person who is coming with the שטר shtar *Shtar*, with
a signed document, which should be evidence itself? So רש"י Rashi *Rashi*
says that that's the assumption we're making in this משנה Mishna *Mishna*,
that the orphans are adults and you would not normally have to
make an oath to collect. Nevertheless what the משנה Mishna *Mishna* is
saying is,
Mrs. the first wife, I guess I'm going to call them רחל
*Rachel*, לאה *Leah*, בלהה *Bilhah*, and זלפה *Zilpah*. So רחל *Rachel*, although
לאה *Leah* of course married first, but okay. Anyway, רחל *Rachel* comes,
the first wife, and she doesn't have to swear to the orphans.
Let them make some oath if they think let them try to,
they're adults, let them try to produce some evidence if they think
part of the כתובה kesuva. *Kesuvah* has been paid. But she does
have to make an oath to לאה *Leah*, זלפה *Zilpah*, and בלהה
*Bilhah*. Because לאה *Leah*, זלפה *Zilpah*, and בלהה *Bilhah* will say to
her, we don't know if maybe that כתובה kesuva, *Kesuva* has been
paid already in parts and in full. And if it has been,
you're seizing the property that we should be getting. So we're losing
out because you're exercising those loans. And therefore you owe us an
oath to us, so that we know you didn't they they're adults,
they're in charge of the father's papers. If they want to make
their claim they can make their claim, if they don't want to
make their claim that's their business. But you by exercising this are
actually risking the property we would seize. You have to make an
oath that it has not been partly paid. Now, מה *Mah* goes
why would we assume that it is true because sometimes the phenomenon
was that some things were partly or fully paid off ahead of
time. I don't know, but nevertheless we know that that's why the
Rabbis in general set an oath when you're coming from orphans that
are minors and maybe according to some even orphans that are adults.
So here put them in a similar situation. Now of course תוספות
Tosafot. *Tosafos* asks, is that true every time a creditor comes? I'm
going to come and collect from saying the guy is dead, let's
say I don't know, the orphans are adults or whatever it is.
Do I have to now make an oath to anybody who has
a future who has a later lien because I'm impacting them? And
the answer there might be no, but here all of them are
in front of us at the same time and that might create
a certain type of a dynamic. Okay, and they're all coming to
collect and they're all sort of seen as a group, whereas individual
because they're all the widow of this man and it's his death
that triggered all of their debt as opposed to people that have
outstanding debts over a long period of time, could have collected them
whenever and they're not related to one another. Okay, so when number
one comes to collect she has to make an oath to two,
three, and four. When two comes to collect she has to make
an oath to three and four, or it actually says to three.
When three comes and collects she makes an oath to number four.
ורביעית נפרעת שלא בשבועה *Veriviis nifres shelo bishvua*. Number four comes in
to collect, nobody is losing out as a result of her again
the orphans are a situation where they're not making her take an
oath or not able to make her take an oath. So she
collects without oaths, nobody is losing out as a result of her.
בן ננס Ben Nanas אומר *Ben Nanos omer*, Ben Nanos says, וכי
מפני שהיא אחרונה *Vachi mipnei shehi achrona*. And the question is like
why? Like, you know, I mean she, nobody is losing out as
a result of her, and and she's getting the dregs, she's getting
whatever's left at the end, so she's not so much נשכרת. That's,
you know, that's what you get for the booby prize for being
the last person to collect, is that you don't have to make
an oath. Okay. Anyway, Ben Nanas doesn't like it. We'll see why
in the גמרא. Gemara,
היו יוצאות כולן ביום אחד. Hayu yotzos kulam b'yom echad. Now, if
let's say all of going back to like the earlier משנה, Mishna
they all had the same date of the כתובה. kesuva They were
all married on the same date. Okay. Now, so at the before
the frame the previous משנה Mishna. was they really were and we
have to figure out how to divide a limited number of assets.
But this משנה Mishna. is focused on on the re- on more
real world cases where they are sequential, but somehow maybe it was
it was all on the same day but sequential. So the משנה
Mishna. says, כל הקודמת לחברתה אפילו שעה אחת זכתה. Kol hakodemes l'chavertah
afilu sha'ah achas zachsa. Even if it's just one hour before or
one minute before, you you that's an earlier lien, okay, and so
you would go by what time of day.
Now, היו כולן יוצאות בשעה אחת,
Hayu kulan
yotzos
b'sha'ah achas, I'm sorry, וכך היו כותבין בירושלים שעות.
v'kach hayu kosvin b'Yerushalayim sha'os.
And they would have the hours written in the doc- in the
documents in ירושלים Yerushalayim at ten o'clock this marriage took place or
whatever. Okay. We don't do that. Now, now,
we're going to have an interesting question in the גמרא, Gemara. which
is how much does it depend on what's written in the document
and how much says it depend on when actually the document was
given over and when actually, you know, the event took place. But
this משנה Mishna. seems that it's all about the date written in
the document, so even in an earlier hour works. Now, if you
didn't have the hours written in the document, היו כולן יוצאות בשעה
אחת, Hayu kulan yotzos b'sha'ah achas, they were in the same hour
or they were written in the same hour, ואין שם אלא מנה
חולקות בשוה, v'ein sham ela maneh cholekos b'shaveh, they divide equally, and
if it's another scenario you could go back to the earlier משנה
about how you get fun divisions about different diff- you know, different
size כתובות kesuvos with limited estates. Okay. But basically, assuming that they
all have the same size כתובה, Ketubah then they're going to divide
it equally. Okay, גמרא. Gemara, במאי קמיפלגי? B'mai kamifligi?
What is the debate with Ben Nanas and the Rabbis about wheth-
about whether number four has to take an oath and why would
she? אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, so Shmuel says, כגון שנמצאת אחת מהן
שדה שאינה שלו. kegon shenimtzes achas meihen sadeh she'einah shelo. I'm going
to read this like תוספות. Tosafot רש"י Rashi says it means literally
the case already is that you discover that one of the wives
one, two, or three, one of their fields that they have seized
actually did not belong to the husband. The husband had, you know,
he had claimed it was his, there was a, you know, evidence
came to light, it was discovered that he had forged a document
or whatever it was, you know, he had innocently bought it and
it turns out that it had been stolen. Anyway, so one of
the fields taken by one of the earlier wives turns out that
it that it was not the husband's and therefore she's not she's
going to have to take a different field now. Now רש"י Rashi,
says that that already has been shown to be the case or
are, you know, or evidence has already been brought to that effect.
תוספות Tosafot reads it and I'm going to read it תוספות Tosafot
way because it
just seems to taken and then evidence is brought to that effect.
Yeah, yeah, but it means that there actually is a case where
we know that this field, one of the fields that one of
them took, is either stolen or there's reason to think it's stolen.
But it's a specific concrete case when that happens. תוספות Tosafot says,
and I think it reads better in the גמרא, Gemara that no,
the debate is a normal case does number four have to take
an oath because of the possibility that there might turn out one
of these times to be a case where an earlier field is
not you know, the a field seized did- was not owned by
the husband. So that's the way תוספות Tosafot. reads it. One, two,
and three took their fields. Does number four have to take an
oath? And I'm going to go with תוספות. Tosafot And Ben Nanas
says she has to take an oath, you know why? It might
turn out that one of those fields that one, two, and three
took were stolen. They're going to have to give it up. Then
they're going to come
to the field that Mrs. Four num- that number four took. She's
not going to want to give it to them. So, but she's
going to owe them an oath, right? So, right, so Bobby, you
come, I'll be I'll be number four, you'll be number three. You
come and you say I lost that field, I have an earlier
I have an earlier lien claim, you give me that field. I'll
say tough luck, you know, I I took my field already for
payment, you can't come and take it from me now. You say
okay, but at least take an oath that you deserve that field,
that your כתובה Ketubah, hasn't been paid up already. Okay. So therefore
Ben Nanas says because of that possib- possibility number four will have
to take an oath to the other wives so that if it
should ever turn out that they're going to want that field or
they're going to say that she impacted them by taking that field,
she'll already have made an oath to them. Okay. Yes.
I'm just thinking biblically for a minute, why does it say it
was stolen? Why couldn't it say it's like he bought it then
it's יובל, Yovel, it goes back and it's...
All right, so fine, we we could try to create another scenario.
Because no, if it's a case of יובל Yovel and things are
working normally, then you get what you know then that's the system
you're playing by.
He's talking about the meaning even if she gets it and she
has to give it back to the...
If that, yeah, I mean if that's... okay, yeah. So okay, so
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: Okay, so that's the issue. ובעל
חוב מאוחר שקדם וגבה קמיפלגי *U-va'al chov me'uchar she-kadum v-gava kamiflegi*.
Now
why did the Rabbis disagree? Because the question is what happens when
a later creditor collects
and it turns out that actually that there was somebody had prior
liens. Is he entitled to keep what he collected? And you can
just imagine a very simple case like this. Guy died, I'm aware,
I read the obituaries every day, I'm aware of or actually you
don't even need the guy to have died actually, but okay, whatever
it is, Michael here has a lien that predates mine, he has
he lent the guy money ten years before me, but I have
decided to go ahead and I've either and I've collected the field.
Okay, and then Michael wakes up and Michael says, "Wait a minute,
that was the only field that guy had, I was first in
line, give me that field!" And I'm saying, "Tough luck, you snooze
you lose, I got it first, right?" So, if we maybe if
we had both come to the court and they saw both of
our documents and then I tried to seize it with them knowing
that you had an earlier claim, that's one thing, but right now
I took it, right when it wasn't even nobody knew you had
an earlier claim, you weren't here pressing your case, so you don't
have a right to take it away from me, or do you?
Okay, so that's the question. So ובעל חוב מאוחר *U-v-va'al chov me'uchar*,
a later creditor comes and takes it, שקדם וגבה *she-kadum v-gava*, that
jumped in front of the line and took, קמיפלגי *kamiflegi*, they're in
debate. תנא קמא Tana Kama סבר *Tana Kamma savar*, תנא קמא Tana
Kama *Tana Kamma* thinks, מה שגבה לא lo, גבה *mah she-gava lo
gava*, that I don't care that you managed to seize it first,
you were a later creditor and now it turns out somebody has
an earlier lien, you're going to have to give it up. So
in this case, number four took the field, because it was the
very last field, and now it turns out that number two says
I was never paid because the field I took was stolen and
this is the very last field available, you gotta give it to
me, right? So תנא קמא Tana Kama *Tana Kamma* says מה שגבה
לא lo, גבה *mah she-gava lo gava*. Yeah, number four will have
to give it now to number two, she's not entitled to keep
it. ובן ננס סבר *U-ven Nanas savar*, בן ננס *Ben Nanas* says,
מה שגבה גבה *mah she-gava gava*. No, what number four took he
can keep. So here's how that plays out in terms of the
שבועה *shvu'ah*. Okay, Bappi comes to me and says, "Turns out my
field was stolen, give it to me." If I say,
"Oh, you're right, unfortunately it's yours. Here, take it. I'm not allowed
to keep it." Then I'll never have to make a שבועה *shvu'ah*
to Bappi because if it turns out that Bappi's going to want
my field, she's going to get my field. So why do I
ever owe a שבועה *shvu'ah* to Bappi? She's always going to be
able right I'm never going to hurt her interests by taking this
field if it doesn't belong to me because if it turns out
she needs it she's just going to take it. Okay, so that's
why according to תנא Tanna. קמא *Tana Kamma* I don't make an
oath to you. But according to בן ננס *Ben Nanas*, Bappi comes
to me and says, "Give me that field." I said,
"I'm sorry, I already took
it, you at the time thought you had collected, turns out you
didn't, I feel bad for you, but I already took it, it's
mine." So then it's like, okay, but now the fact that you're
holding onto it is hurting her interests, is hurting my interests. So
at least make me an oath that you did not already have
your debt paid up. So בן ננס *Ben Nanas* who says make
an oath, it's again, it's because he's entitled to keep the field.
Whereas תנא Tanna, קמא *Tana Kamma* says she doesn't make an oath,
it says she'll never be entitled to keep that field if an
earlier wife deserves it and therefore why should she ever need to
make an oath? Okay, so that's the debate.
Yeah, to keep people honest, because if the fourth one doesn't have
to swear maybe she got paid already, and then she keeps and
then
who's she being honest to? To the orphans? Yeah, that's a different
discussion. That's why I started by saying we're assuming the orphans are
adults and if there's an issue that they think they're being cheated
let them come ahead and make their case.
No but even the mothers want their sons to get as much
inheritance as they can, so because whatever's not taken as the debt
is going to be divided...
So that's the orphans' issue, so that's let them make her make
an oath. This is not about the orphans.
Okay, that's answer number one about the so. רב נחמן Rav Nachman
אמר רבה בר אבוה *Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha*, דכולי עלמא
d'chulei alma, מה שגבה לא גבה *d-chulei alma mah she-gava lo gava*.
Everybody would agree that if it turns out that one of the
earlier fields was stolen, number four cannot keep her field. She'll have
to give it to the woman who now hasn't collected her debt
yet. והכא בחוששין שמא תחסיף קמיפלגי *V-hacha b-choshishin shema tachsif kamiflegi*. The
question is whether number four will basically strip mine the field, ruin
the field. מר סבר חחוששין שמא תחסיף *Mar savar choshishin shema tachsif*,
we're afraid, ומר סבר לא חחוששין שמא תחסיף *v-mar savar lo choshishin
shema tachsif*, we're not afraid. So here's the way it works out.
I take the field and it was the very last field and
I also know now again it's a little funny if there hasn't
already been raised the possibility that an earlier one might be stolen
why I would even think to start worrying about this but okay
let's say there's some murmurings around or whatever and or I just
know about my dead husband that there might be one of those
fields was stolen. So here I am, I took this field and
I know what's going to happen, what's going to happen is if
one of those fields were stolen that one of the other wives
took, I'm going to have to give it up. So what am
I going to do for the period that it's in my possession?
I'm going to strip mine it, I'm going to try to squeeze
it dry and get as much as I can while it's under
my control. Okay? So that's what we're concerned that number four is
going to do. So therefore what... so therefore... paid. So therefore now
it becomes even very tricky. So what does an oath have anything
to do with it? So בן ננס says like this: If we
make number four take an oath to one, two, and three that
my כתובה Ketubah has not been paid, what psychologically will number four
think? She'll think I'm never gonna I'm gonna be entitled to keep
my field, right? She'll think why am I making an oath to
them? They'll just take my field away if they haven't had their
debt paid out. If I make an oath to them, it must
mean that if they have some claim against me, I'm gonna be
able to keep the field. So by making her take an oath,
we're having her think, it's very, it's very bizarre, right? We're duping
her to think that she'll be able to keep the field if
they have a claim against her, even though she won't, but that'll
make her think obviously if I'm taking an oath it's cause I'll
be entitled to keep it. And therefore she won't strip mine and
squeeze the field dry.
Selling stuff they know is no good.
There you go.
Or she can say I will, because I'll be able to keep
it, you know?
What? She won't be able to keep it and everybody agrees she
can't keep it. But we make her, and if she knew that,
then she
would strip mine it. So therefore, we'll have her take an oath
so she thinks that the only reason I'd be taking an oath
is I'd be allowed to keep it, so she'll handle her field
properly. Yes.
Does this remind you of the תוספות Tosafot that you should still
keep the
Torah?
Right.
Yeah, so she won't know, right. And then find loopholes, right. Wait,
is this just a kind of
thing for women? Yeah, it's a good question. I mean it does
get back, I don't know, I don't know. I mean it is
true that sometimes the גמרא Gemara makes this assumption by men as
well, but it does raise the point that תוספות Tosafot points out
that we never have any of these discussions about oaths or anything,
you know, by case of male creditors or just normal creditors. I
mean it could be women, but if they're women creditors as opposed
to women who are collecting their כתובה, Ketubah right, this we only
find this in like the כתובה scenario. So that's unusual, and תוספות
Tosafos tries to figure that out. Yeah. Next question.
Wait, isn't this a little bit of dishonesty going on?
I mean, right, well that's the point, that's why I used the
word dupe, which is we tell her, now, we don't tell her
why we're making her take an oath and you could say
look, nobody's being hurt by this. If she really had some of
her כתובה already paid, then she shouldn't be collecting. The orphans might
be being hurt. Now for whatever reason,
as I said initially, she's not taking an oath to the orphans.
They're adults or whatever. Okay. But bottom line is, it's not she's
not losing anything, right? We're just saying you want to collect, you
make an oath. It's true in principle the oaths are really to
the other wives, and here you don't have to make an oath
to the other wives if you really knew what was going on.
But at the end of the day, all we're asking you to
do is to make it clear that you're entitled, you know, to
what you're collecting. So I think that has to be appreciated. It
might be technically she doesn't owe an oath to the wives, but
bottom line all she's doing is she's swearing that she's entitled to
collect. Alright? If the fact along the way that that helps her
think that she's gonna be able to keep the field and that
helps serves other types of purposes, wonderful. Okay? But I think we
have to appreciate that we're not making her lose anything. We're only
making her swear that she's entitled to collect what she's collecting.
The name of it anyway is swear.
I understand, so technically she's not obligated, so we're gonna make her
obligated. There's some benefit that's being served, but it's not like we're
doing her this great disservice. Okay? And I think that has to
be appreciated that there's no disservice being done, or not a great
disservice. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר אביי,
Amar Abaye, אביי Abaye says,
אביי דקשישא, Abaye Dekashisha,
where was it? איכא בינייהו. Ika Benaihu. No, they're debating
the position of the elder אביי. Abaye. I don't know, apparently there
was an elder אביי Abaye who was a תנא. Tanna דתניא, Detanya,
it seems like, no, or not תנא, Tanna. excuse me, but he
taught the ברייתא. Braita. דתני אביי קשישא, Detani Abaye Kashisha, the elder
אביי Abaye taught: יתומים שאמרו גדולים, Yetomim She'amru Gedolim, when they said
that the elder, or no, it sounds like he actually is the
תנא who is saying this. So it's interesting, אביי's Abaye name of
a תנא. Anyway, יתומים שאמרו, Yetomim She'amru,
the heirs when they said that you have to take an oath
when you collect from orphans, so which type of orphans do you
have to take an oath from if you're a creditor or a
widow? גדולים, Gedolim, even if they're adults, אין צריך לומר קטנים, Ein
Tsariach Lomar Ketanim, it goes without saying if they're minors. Okay, so
this is the question: do you take an oath to adult orphans?
תנא קמא לית ליה דאביי קשישא, Tana Kama Leit Lei De'abaye Kashisha,
the תנא קמא doesn't agree with that. The תנא קמא says they're
adults so you don't. So the question is number four doesn't have
to take an oath to one, two, and three, but does she
have to take an oath to the orphans? Right? So the תנא
קמא holds no, the orphans are adults, you don't owe them an
oath. בן ננס אית ליה דאביי קשישא Ben Nanas Ait Lei De'abaye
Kashisha and בן ננס says forget wives one, two, and three. They
all have to swear to the orphans, I don't care if they're
kids or adults. So that's a much simpler issue, right? Does she
owe an oath to the orphans? So four doesn't owe it to
the previous wives, does she owe it to the orphans? אמר רב
הונא, Amar Rav Huna, says רב הונא: Rav Huna: הכי תני אביי,
Hachi Tani Abaye, the elder אביי Abaye taught. הני תרי אחי ותרי
שותפי, Hani trei achei vetrei shutfei, and this is going to be
interesting. You have two brothers who are effectively now who inherited an
estate and they haven't divided it, so effectively
they're partners in the estate, right? Until the estate is divided, they're
joint owners of the estate. Or you just have two partners in
a business, in a field let's say. איתו דינא בהדי חד, Eitu
dina bahadei chad, and they have a court case with a guy.
A guy comes and he has some case that he's bringing against
the heirs of the estate, the undivided estate, or he's bringing against
the owners of this field, and there are multiple
owners, ואזל חד מינייהו בהדי לדינא, veazal chad mineihu bahadei ledina, and
one of them
goes to court with him. And we don't know where the other
owner is. And then the guy who has the claim wins in
court. לא מצי אידך למימר ליה, Lo matzi idach lemeimar lei, the
other partner can't say to the guy who won the court case:
את לאו בר דין דידי את. At lav bar din didi at.
You know, you won the court case against my partner, so you
won against his half of the field. Okay, but you didn't win
against my half of the field. If you want to claim on
what I own of the partnership, you know, I would have made
a better defense and you're going to have to bring me to
that case, right? Which is an interesting question, right? I mean nowadays
I guess it doesn't work, it doesn't happen because people assign a
lawyer, and the lawyer is representing the essentially, you know, is representing
the entire defendants or the entire litigant, the entire claim. But here
you would go and you would defend yourself. So if you're only
half of, you own half of it, are you representing the whole
thing implicitly or only representing your half? So he says implicitly he
was representing the whole thing. So he can't,
you can't say: Look, you only won against my partner. לא מצי
אידך למימר את לאו בעל דברים דידי את, Lo matzi idach lemeimar
at lav ba'al devarim didi at, אלא שליחותיה עביד. ela shelichusei avad.
But
no, we assume that the partner was basically representing the entire estate,
the entire property. Okay, now let's take a look if that's always
true. איקלע רב נחמן לסורא, Iklah Rav Nachman le-Sura, רב נחמן Rav
Nachman dropped into סורא. Sura.
שיילו כהאי גוונא, She'eilu ke-hai gavna, they asked him what would be
the story in this type of a case. מאי, Mai, what's the
story? אמר להו, Amar lehu, he said, מתניתין היא, matnisin hi, we
can learn it from our
משנה. הראשונה נשבעת לשניה ושניה לשלישית ושלישית לרביעית, Ha-rishona nishba'at la-shniya ve-shniya
la-shlishit ve-shlishit la-revi'it, one swears to two, two to three, three to
four. ואילו ראשונה לשלישית לא תני, Ve-ilu rishona la-shlishit lo tnei, but
why doesn't one also have to swear to three? Because one taking
the field is who's being hurt by one taking the field? Not
potentially, not just number two, but also number three and number four.
So why doesn't she have to make an oath to all of
them? It must be that when she makes an oath to number
two, number two is representing all of those people that have interests
in the field. So the גמרא Gemara says: מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama,
why is she not making an oath to three and four? לאו
משום דשליחותא עבדה, Lav mishum de-shlichusa avda, it must be two represents
three and four. So you see that there's that implicit representing the
other parties. So the גמרא Gemara says: No, מי דמי, mi dami,
who can compare them? התם, Hatam, שבועה לאחד שבועה למאה. shvua le-echad
shvua le-me'ah. If you make one oath, why should I have to
make the same oath to number two and to number three and
to number four? The oath basically makes it clear to the court
and to anybody who might be interested that it's not evidence. I
can't bring evidence that something hasn't happened. Okay, but it backs up
my claim if anybody had any doubt that I might be lying.
So I took an oath that hopefully will alleviate some doubts that
I might be making this up. Okay, so why do different people
deserve different oaths? I made the oath, right? So whatever sort of
evidence that produces that it assuages some, you know, that I'm probably
telling the truth, you know, that should serve for whoever has that,
who wants to claim maybe I'm lying. If I were lying, I
wouldn't have made an oath. Who cares who I made the oath
to? I wouldn't have taken God's name in vain if I was
lying, right? So who cares that you didn't hear the oath? I
made it. That should be good for anybody who cares. Okay, now
it is interesting that the גמרא Gemara thought otherwise because the גמרא
Gemara sometimes does feel, and we actually had this phrase earlier, that
sometimes you take an oath להפיסי דעתו של בעל הבית. la-hafosei da'ato
she-ba'al ha-bayit. Like not to objectively bring evidence: Look, I'll bring evidence
that I'm not lying because I wouldn't have taken God's name in
vain if I was lying, but at the end of the day,
to at least satisfy the other side. You know, so it's not
like some objective evidence that I'm most likely telling the truth, but
it's like: I'm suspicious of you. You make me an oath. Fine.
At least you sort of satisfied, you've given me something. So if
you see it more like you owe me an oath, then you've
well, you owe me an oath, but the other woman said: I
didn't get an oath. You, I want to hear you say that,
and now I want to hear you say that. So that seems
to be what the גמרא Gemara was going for, the idea that
an oath somehow is owed to a person. The person actually gets
the oath from you as opposed to just it brought some, you
know, it made it more, it made it, you know, it brought
some evidence to the fact that I was probably telling the truth.
All right, so therefore that's the גמרא's Gemara response. Response is you
cannot say two is representing... You don't have to say two is
representing three and four. You can just say once an oath was
made, it was made. Who cares who else was in the room?
Okay. שבועה לאחד שבועה למאה, Shvua le-echad shvua le-me'ah, an oath for
one is an oath for a hundred.
Saying it's more people would impress upon you, you
know... Maybe magnitude?
Well, that could be too. Okay, that's another point as well just
in terms of the evidence point if you have to do it
multiple times, you know, you'll more okay. But you can also say
ולמה u-le-mah force you to admit something that you're not really guilty
of. Anyway, הכא אמר, hacha amar, here you'll say that so there
you made the oath, end of story. But here, the other partner
can say אילו אנא הוה תבנא, ilu ana hava tavna, if I
was there, טעיננא טפי, teinna tfei, I would have made a better
claim. So, you know, so just because he didn't do a good
job representing himself, I have other evidence to bring. So the Gemara
says therefore why should I lose out based on the my half
based on, you know, what he did? Okay, so that's very reasonable.
So then the Gemara
says ולא אמרינן, ve-lo amrinan, so now the Gemara's inclined towards
towards, you know, this new point against what we had said before,
that actually the other guy doesn't lose out, that the one the
one partner is not the implicit representative of the of the whole
estate, and the other guy is able to say I'm entitled to
my day in court. But even but that we don't say אלא
דלא איתא במתא, ella d'lo ite b'mata, if you weren't in the
city when the court case was taking place. אבל איתא במתא, aval
ite b'mata, if you were in the city, איבעי ליה למיתי, ibai
leh l'meisei, why didn't you show up in court? Okay? So that's
the question of you cannot assume de facto one partner represents the
whole estate, but you can look at the context and say does
the context show us that implicitly you were empowering him to represent
you? And sometimes the answer is yes and sometimes the answer is
no. But we have to have evidence that you were implicitly empowering
him to represent you, otherwise he's entitled to say he was only
representing his half, not my half. Wait, wait, Michael had a question.
Okay, yeah.
If he were in town, the second person, and he was seriously
ill, would that change?
Yeah, presumably yes. These are not like categorical. What the Gemara is
saying is now we're going to start looking at context, right? We're
not going to say de facto he represents, we're going to say
implicitly there are times when he might implicitly represent and then we're
going to have to see when that's true. The de facto assumption
is that he's not representing the other half unless there's some evidence
to be brought that would indicate that implicitly he is. Okay. If
I were fighting the case, the first thing I would want to
do before the case proceeded would be to clarify that point: whether
the other side is representing the whole estate or only half of
it. All right, איתמר. itmar. Now we're going to turn to something
which is, you know, loosely connected to the Mishnah about parallel ktubot,
or not so loosely, right? The ktubot at the same time, you
divide it equally. So now, when here's the here's
I just want to sort of set up how this is going
to be similar to the Mishnah but different. The Mishnah is the
two wives have identical liens on the same field. There is no
question that both of them are entitled, both of those of the
of the shtaros of the documents are correct, are true, are accurate,
the guy owed a hundred dollars to each wife, and they're both
in principle entitled to the full hundred dollars. The only problem is
that there's limited assets. So what do you do? They each have
a full and just claim on the hundred dollars, they can't both
get you can't get more than a hundred dollars out of it,
so you'll divide their claims, each one gets half, right? That's what
the Mishnah says. What when it's land and the claims is well
that could be a claim on land but it's a lien on
land but when it's a claim about who did the guy sell
it to, then they're not only one of them is really deserves
it, right? If it's not like they both the so that's going
to be the case. Two people have deeds of sale for the
same date for the same plot of land. Okay? So there, it's
a different case. It's not obvious we would split it because one
guy was really sold to and the other guy was duped and
we just don't know which is which. Okay? So let's take a
look. איתמר בי שטרות היוצאין ביום אחד. itmar bei shtaros hayotzin b-yom
echad. Two documents that are issued on the same day and again
the implicit point here is for the same thing. Okay. רב אמר
חולקין. Rav amar cholkin. Okay. What can you do? You split it.
Which is an interesting question, right? Do we go for something that
might match the facts? There is no way the assumption is that
this matches the facts. Okay? Because, you
know, either it was all sold to A or all sold to
B. So there's no way this actually matches the facts but given
that we're not going to we don't know how to you know
there's no way we can actually, you know, know what the facts
are, this is the most judicious, you know, resolution of this case
even though it's not it's clearly will not be true in terms
of what the actual facts were. ושמואל אמר שודא דדייני. u-Shmuel amar
shuda de-dayni. No actually the judges get to make an arbitrary decision.
They sort of they cast their decision. Now there's a ques- debate
about Rashi and Tosafot how do they how do they make their
decision. Rashi says: we can't tell you any rules, you're going to
have to basically look at the circumstances and do your make your
best judgment.
Who did he know better?
Whose story who story seemed who story seems more credible? Whose story
seems to cohere more? You know, other type we're going to look
at it and we're just going to make our best guess. But
Shmuel's basic point is you got to try to have it match
what actually happened. Even okay, it could be a hundred percent wrong,
right? Rav knows, Rav knows my deci- it's like a if it's
like a compromise, right? Everybody leaves unhappy. Rav knows I know that
my decision is always going to be fifty percent wrong, but it's
always always going to be
fifty percent right. I want to go for the 100%. I want
to go for the gold. So I'm going to try to get
it all right, it might be all wrong, but I'm going to
try to get it all right. Okay, that's what שמואל Shmuel says,
and we'll do the best we can. Every, the judges will decide
the best they can. Now תוספות Tosafos. says שודא דדייני shuda d'dayni
actually is not you look at the, they look at the circumstances
and they try to make the best decision. שמואל Shmuel actually says
שודא דדייני shuda d'dayni is they just give it to whoever they,
whoever they want to give it to, right? Because it's basically all
arbitrary. It's, it's as we say a coin toss, a crapshoot. Either
it'll be right or it won't be right. So we'll just do
what we, you know, maybe one guy is poor and the other
guy is rich, so we'd rather the poor guy had it. Maybe
one guy is a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham and the other person
isn't. Maybe who knows why. I know it's very, it's deeply disturbing,
this, this idea. But we'll make an arbitrary decision and we'll hope
it'll be right. Okay, I can't defend תוספות. Tosafot Okay, לימא? leima?
So I'm going to assume what?
The גמרא Gemara says that, that
he's, the
גמרא Gemara indicates that. Okay, לימא רב דאמר כרבי מאיר, leima Rav
damar k'Rabbi Meir, דאמר, damar, now we're going to try to understand
what the debate is about. רב Rav goes like רבי מאיר, Rabbi
Meir, דאמר עדי חתימה כרתי. damar aidei chasima karsi. The, the signatories
of the document are what make it binding. Now the word כרתי
karsi really comes from the word כריתות, krisus, which is a גט,
get, a book, a document of division, of separation, because this debate
starts with the issue of a גט. get. And the question is
you do two things by a גט. get. A document is signed
and it's handed over in front of live witnesses. And the debate
is who are the real witnesses of the גט? get? רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says the signatories are, עדי חתימה כרתי. aidei chasima karsi.
The witnesses who are חותמים, chosmim, who signed their names, are the
ones that make it a גט. get. And רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar
says no, עדי מסירה כרתי, aidei mesira karsi, the witnesses of the
handing over are the ones that make it a גט, get, the
ones that witness the גט get being handed over. And the obvious
question is, let's say you have one pair of witnesses without the
other, is the גט get still good? That's one obvious difference. Here
the difference is going to be that the document, if you say
עדי חתימה כרתי, aidei chasima karsi, the document is defined totally in
terms of not when it was actually given, but in terms of
what it says. And they both say the exact same thing, so
no other facts are relevant. Okay, they basically, you know, even if
one, we can prove one was given before the other, it won't
matter. The document, the effect of the document, right, the way it
has legal effect is through what the testimony that it states, and
therefore they're completely equal. So רב, Rav, who says you divide it,
says bottom line here is we have two documents that took effect
simultaneously and in contradictory ways. There is no better resolution. It's not
like one guy, so as opposed to what I said, I'm always
going to be 50% wrong, רב Rav says I'm not always going
to be 50% wrong, because one guy didn't get it and the
other guy did. They both basically essentially got
it because both documents took effect simultaneously and contradictorily, so the, so
therefore they both got 50% out of it. That's what רב Rav
says. Okay, but it's not like one person is the real owner
and the other person isn't. ושמואל, v'Shmuel, now שמואל Shmuel דאמר כרבי
אלעזר. damar k'Rabbi Elazar. He goes like רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, דאמר
עדי מסירה כרתי. damar aidei mesira karsi. It's when the, by case
of a גט, get, the גט get was handed over, and therefore
it doesn't matter that the documents say the same thing. Who did
I give the document to first is the one who owns the
field. So there is a true owner and there's a guy who's
not a true owner. And therefore we just don't know, and therefore
we're going to do, try to do, guess who the right owner
is. So that's what the גמרא Gemara thinks the debate is about.
So the גמרא Gemara says לא, not necessarily.
Do you think it could be whoever's like, you know, closer or
further? That'd be one way of doing it.
Maybe. לא, דכולי עלמא, I mean even if you have a representative,
דכולי עלמא כרבי אלעזר. d'chulei alma k'Rabbi Elazar. Everybody could say like
רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, which is that there is one true owner.
It goes by who got it first. We don't know who that
is. והכא בהאי קמיפלגי. v'hacha b'hai kamifligi. רב סבר חלוקה עדיפא, Rav
savar chaluka adifa, שמואל סבר שודא דדייני עדיפא. Shmuel savar shuda d'dayni
adifa. I think that's a more interesting debate, right? No, there definitely
is one real owner and not one real owner. What's the best
way to figure, to deal with it when you don't know who's
who and there's no evidence about who's who? So רב Rav says
like I said, split it, it'll always be 50% wrong, but it'll
always be 50% right. And שמואל Shmuel says you try to figure
out who the real owner is. Okay, so that's the issue.
If you have two, couldn't you say that the last, the last
deal you make is the right one?
No, that's the whole point, we don't know which the last deal
is. Oh, why, you mean if we did know which one? No,
because if I've already handed it over, I've already handed it over.
It's no longer my field to sell. Okay, so there, so everybody
says there is, according to this, there is one true owner, but
the question is what do you do when you have no evidence
about it and the evidence is contradictory? So do you split it
or do you try to figure out who's who? I assume what
does a court do? I assume the court, like, imagine if a
case like that came to the court, right? Would they basically
try to figure out who the real owner was, and if they
felt that they could not determine it, would they still have to
just, would they be able to say the evidence
is all... Right, but if it's not arbitration, if you actually bring
it to a court, right?
But
they don't do that. In a court there's a winner and a
loser. What?
Right. The court would never say 50-50. The court wouldn't say all
the evidence is contradictory, we're throwing up our hands 50-50.
They would, you're saying
they're deadlocked, right,
but they'd have to make, they'd have to decide. They'd have to
decide.
But let me just understand one thing over here. Yeah? So this
is חולקין את השדה, cholkin es hasadeh, right? Right. But if you
do it 50-50, then will the others still get back the money?
In other words, because if I sold it to you, I gave
this guy, you took 2000 for him, you took... yeah, so you
still took money, you know what I mean? So you still gotta
make them whole.
Yeah, that's an interesting question.
So, and the field is worth 2000 or whatever...
yeah, I don't know, that's an interesting... yeah, it's also an interesting
case, sort of like the, you know, the שלמה Shlomo and the
baby.
It's an interesting case. I don't know, because if one of the
documents is fake, is it fake and no money was ever given,
or is it fake and the guy was duped? I don't know
the answer to that.
Because then they go after the other...
All right, yeah, that's a good question. It's a very good question.
I don't know the answer. Anyway, let's see how the גמרא Gemara
continues. It sounds like no. Okay, yeah, so let's see how the
גמרא Gemara continues. Okay. ומי מצית מוקמת לה כרבי אליעזר? Umi matzis
mokmas lah k'Rabbi Eliezer?
Now can you really say that they both hold like רבי אליעזר,
Rabbi Eliezer, that one of the guys owns the field, it goes
to the guy who got it first, and the question is how
do you best divide it? והאמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Veha'amar Rav
Yehuda amar Rav, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said in the name of
רב, Rav, הלכה כרבי אליעזר בגיטין. Halacha k'Rabbi Eliezer b'Gittin. We rule
like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer by a גט. get. כי אמריתה קמי
דשמואל, Ki amritah kamei d'Shmuel, and when it was said in front
of שמואל, Shmuel, says רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, because he was a
student of both רב Rav and שמואל, Shmuel, אמר אף בשטרות. amar
af b'shtaros. We rule like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that goes by
when it was handed over and the witnesses of the handing over,
not just by a גט, get, but even by other שטרות. shtaros.
All right. מכלל, Michlal, that means that we can then infer that
when רב Rav says we go like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer by
a גט, get, he meant only by a גט. get. דרב סבר
בשטרות לא. D'Rav savar b'shtaros lo. Okay, so רב Rav basically holds
we rule by רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer only by a גט get
but not by שטרות. shtaros. So it's pretty clear that what we
said originally was correct: רב Rav holds like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
and שמואל Shmuel holds like רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. אלא מחוורתא רב
כרבי מאיר ושמואל כרבי אליעזר. Ela machvarta Rav k'Rabbi Meir u'Shmuel k'Rabbi
Eliezer.
Fine, that seems very clear that that actually matches their positions about
what makes a document binding. So רב Rav would say it's the
testimony and the witnesses in the document, and therefore these documents are
completely equal and they both really do own the field, nobody really,
it wouldn't matter who got the document first. And שמואל Shmuel says
no, it matters who got the document first, and therefore we have
to figure out who the one is that really owns it. All
right, let's take a look. מיתיבי. Meseivi. שני שטרות היוצאים ביום אחד.
Sheni shtaros hayotzim b'yom echad. We got a ברייתא. braisa. Two documents
that come out on the same field and they have the same
dates on them. חולקין. Cholkin. You divide it. תיובתא דשמואל. Tiyuvta d'Shmuel.
That's a contradiction to שמואל Shmuel because it says explicitly you divide
it. Now, of course שמואל Shmuel could say the obvious answer. אמר
לך שמואל הא מני רבי מאיר היא. Amar lach Shmuel ha mani
Rabbi Meir hi. I just got through telling you, says שמואל, Shmuel,
that I follow רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. That that split, that's רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir who says that the documents are both valid and
equal and therefore you split it. ואנא דאמרי כרבי אליעזר. Va'ana d'amri
k'Rabbi Eliezer. I say like רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. And who says
that? One of them owns it, whoever got it first, and we
have to try to figure it out. But wait one minute. אי
רבי מאיר, I Rabbi Meir, if that ברייתא braisa is רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir that says it goes by the signatures of the גט
get and by what the שטר shtar and what the שטר shtar
testifies, אימא סיפא, eima seifa, let's look at the end of it.
כתב לאחד ומסר לאחר. Kasav l'echad u'masar l'acher. I wrote for ראובן
Reuven first and signed it, had witnesses sign it, but then before
I gave it to ראובן, Reuven, לאחר, l'acher, excuse me, and then
before I gave it to ראובן, Reuven, I wrote the same parallel
document for שמעון Shimon and gave it to שמעון. Shimon. So שמעון
Shimon got it first, but ראובן's Reuven was dated earlier. Got it?
So this is the question: do you go by the dating of
the document or the giving of the document? The signing, dating of
the document or the giving of the document? What does the ברייתא
braisa say? It says זה שמסר לו קנה. zeh shemasar lo kanah.
The one who received it first gets it. So whose position is
that? That's רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that says you go by when
it was handed over, עדי מסירה. eidei mesira. So you see the
same ברייתא braisa that says that it does go by when it
was handed over and there is a real owner to the field
still says you split it, which is רב's Rav position. אי רבי
מאיר, I Rabbi Meir, if it's רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, אמאי קנה?
amai kanah? Why would the guy who received it first get it?
האמר עדי חתימה כרתי. Ha'amar eidei chasima karsi. He would say the
witnesses who sign make it an effective document and therefore it should
go to the person whose document was first signed, not whose document
was first received. So you see that this ברייתא braisa is like
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, that you go by when the document was
received, and even though one person therefore really does own the field
and the other one does not, because it really is a question
of who received it first, nevertheless the ברייתא braisa says you do
not give it all to one person. So the person says you
split it, so that's a challenge to שמואל. Shmuel. So אמר לך
שמואל Amar lekha Shmuel with this דלית ליה, dalit lei, so אידך
מיבעיא ליה idach miba'ia lei תנאי. tannai. Fine, says שמואל, Shmuel, you've
proven that there's a position out there that if you go by
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, you split it. But I'm going to tell
you it's a debate of תנאים tannaim how you deal with these
cases, whether you split or whether you give it to one person.
דתניא, De-tanya, we learn in a ברייתא. braita. וחכמים אומרים יחלוקו. Ve-chachamim
omrim yachloku. It's a case where a שליח shaliach was sent to
deliver money and when the people he came to had died, and
then he went back to the person who sent him and the
person who sent him had died, and there was a whole question
about figuring out where that money was supposed to go. Okay, so
the sages say you split it between the heirs of the person
who sent him and the person it was headed to. וכאן אמרו,
Ve-chan amru, but here in בבל Bavel we said מה שירצה שליש
יעשה, Ma she-yirtsa shelish ya'aseh, that the agent can basically do what
he thinks is right, and that is an indication to תוספות's Tosafot,
idea of like do what you want with it. You gotta give
it to one of them, who knows who, you figure it out.
Okay, so basically he says that's a parallel to this issue. There
is competing claims, there's no way of knowing who deserves it, only
one side deserves it, what do you do? Split it or make
your best decision? Okay, so the same way that's true over there,
and that's not a case of a court case, that's a case
about somebody sent with money and he's got the money and he's
gotta figure out what to do with it, but nevertheless he wants
to know from the court what should I do with it, and
they'll say well either split it or just figure it out for
yourself. Okay, so therefore that's what שמואל Shmuel says. So basically we
have two reasons to say split. You could say split because it
all goes by when the document is signed and therefore the two
people with the document really do equally own the field, so we're
going to split it, or they equally don't own the field or
whatever, but we're going to split it, or it goes by when
the document was handed over, one person really owns it, and then
you could go either way. You could say, 'Okay, one person owns
it, we don't know who, we'll split it,' or 'One person owns
it, we don't know who, we'll make our best guess.' שמואל Shmuel
says best guess, but there is a ברייתא, braita, there is an
opinion out there that says you actually do split it in that
case.
Just a contrast between the first case which was done deceitfully and
here with the money...
that's a good point. You're right, maybe we would treat it differently
because one of them here right here we don't know what the
dead person was intending, but there was no deceit here, yeah that's
a very good point. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this,
now we'll have some application to this. אימי דרמי בר חמא, Immei
de-Rami bar Chama, the mother of רמי בר חמא Rami bar Chama
כתבינהו לנכסה, kasvin'hu le-nichsah, she wrote over her property לרמי בר חמא
בצפרא le-Rami bar Chama be-tsafra to her son רמי בר חמא Rami
bar Chama in the morning. לאורתא Le-orta towards evening time, it wasn't
yet night time, it was the same הלכהic halacha day, כתבינהו למר
עוקבא בר חמא, kasvin'hu le-Mar Ukva bar Chama, she wrote it over
to her other son. All right. So and then presumably she died
and now they're going to fight over their mother's property. אתא רמי
בר חמא לקמיה דרב ששת, Ata Rami bar Chama le-kamei de-Rav Sheshet,
רמי בר חמא Rami bar Chama came to רב ששת, Rav Sheshet,
said, 'Look, here's this document I got from my mother עליה השלום
aleha ha-shalom and she wrote over it all
to me first in the morning whatever.' אוקמיה בנכסי, Ukmiah be-nichsei, he
said good, he gave him, he awarded him the estate. אתא מר
עוקבא, Ata Mar Ukva, it's not even clear if
מר עוקבא Mar Ukva was even there, רמי בר חמא Rami bar
Chama just went with his document to רב ששת, Rav Sheshet, okay,
אתא מר עוקבא Ata Mar Ukva who was the guy who got
it second לקמיה דרב נחמן, le-kamei de-Rav Nachman, he was רב נחמן
Rav Nachman with his document. Like it seems like they're all just
going unilaterally and producing their documents in different courts. Okay, so what
did רב נחמן Rav Nachman do? So לקמיה דרב נחמן אוקמיה בנכסי,
le-kamei de-Rav Nachman ukmiah be-nichsei, so רב נחמן Rav Nachman awarded him
the
estate. אתא רב ששת לקמיה דרב נחמן, Ata Rav Sheshet le-kamei de-Rav
Nachman, so I might have been being a little facetious, it sounds
like they were aware what was going on, so maybe both of
them did come to both courts. Anyway at the end of the
day רב ששת Rav Sheshet who had ruled in favor of רמי
בר חמא Rami bar Chama the first one came to רב נחמן
Rav Nachman and said אמר ליה מאי טעמא עבד מר הכי? amar
lei mai ta'ama avad mar hachi? 'Why did you do this? Why
did you give it to the... to who was the second one?
מר עוקבא. Mar Ukva. Why did you give it to מר עוקבא?
Mar Ukva? He got it second, you should have given it to
רמי
בר חמא.' Rami bar Chama. אמר ליה ומאי טעמא עבד מר הכי?
Amar lei u-mai ta'ama avad mar hachi? 'And why did you give
it to רמי בר חמא?' Rami bar Chama? אמר ליה דקדים. Amar
lei de-kadim. 'What do you mean why I give it to him?
Because he... he had it written over to him first. He was
first in line, he was the one that got it.' אמר ליה
אטו בירושלים יתבינן דכתבינן שעות? Amar lei atu be-Yerushalayim yasvinan de-kasvinan sha'os?
'I don't get it, you
think we're in ירושלים Yerushalayim where we write the hours in the
document? So even if he got it first, the document both have
the same date in it.' Okay, so here basically he's ruling like
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, right? We go by not when the document
was handed over, we go by the actual date in the document,
and he says I don't care who got it first and it
was written first, they both have the same date in it. Okay,
so that's his position. If you go by רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
now of course if you go by רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir what
should you say? Until now we've been saying יחלוקו. yachloku. All right,
so let's take a look. אמר ליה אלא מר מאי טעמא עבד
הכי? Amar lei ela mar mai ta'ama avad hachi? 'Why did you
do this? Why did you award it all to the second guy?'
אמר ליה שודא דדייני. Amar lei shuda de-dayni. 'Because I'm a judge,
I get to decide who to award it to. Now this is
funny because it sounds like a new position that we haven't been
dealing with yet, that you're holding...' Like רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, you
go by what's in the document. They're both the same, it's the
same date, and nevertheless it's not divided. You're nevertheless still allowed to
award it to one and not the other. Okay, that's a new
position. Until now we've even assumed if it's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
and you go by the documents themselves and what they say, and
then you have to divide. Okay, so he says, I get to
decide. אמר ליה Amar lei חדא- chada I mean, so he says,
אמר ליה Amar lei שודא... shuda... אמר ליה Amar lei אנא נמי
שודא דדייני. Ana nami shuda de'dayanei. Okay, great, so it's the judge's
decision. So I made my decision. He came to me first. The
case came to me first. I said give it to him because
he was first. You say oh no, it doesn't go by who
got it first, they're the same document blah blah blah. Fine. What
would that lead to? That the judge gets to make a decision.
I made a decision. Okay, so it should still go by what
I said. So אמר ליה, amar lei, he said back to him,
חדא, chada, number one, דאנא דיינא ומר לאו דיינא. de'ana dayana u'mar
lav dayana. Number one, I'm a real judge, you're not a real
judge. Okay, so you have to be a- so רב נחמן Rav
Nachman said. Now רב נחמן Rav Nachman was- was the expert...
Well that's the point, so
רב נחמן Rav Nachman was really an expert judge. If you look
at רש"י, Rashi רש"י Rashi says, אנא דיינא ana dayana like two
lines before the lines- three lines before they get wide, רש"י says,
אפי ריש גלותא וריש גלותא דבי ישיבה. a-pi resh galuta ve-resh galuta
d'bei yeshiva. I really am the major authority, I've been appointed by
the political heads, I've been recognized in the, you know, you know,
by the rabbinic, you know, sort of institutions. I am the one
that is the supreme authority. Okay, so I trump you, it sounds
like what he's saying. If you look at תוספות, Tosafot תוספות Tosafot
says like this: פירוש ר"ח דקבלה בידנא perush rach de-kibbala bi-yadana
two lines from the bottom, okay, דקבלה בידנא, de-kibbala bi-yadana, we have
a tradition דשודא דדייני דוקא במקרקעי. d'shuda de'dayanei davka be-mekarkei.
Number one, only when you're dealing with land, not when you're dealing
with chattel, is this- this idea that the judges get to decide
arbitrarily or whatever based on their best guess. ודוקא דיין מומחה כרב
נחמן בדורו. ve-davka dayan mumche ke-Rav Nachman be-doro.
And only the most expert judge in the generation. דהא רב ששת
גברא רבה הוה. de'ha Rav Sheshet gavra rabba hava. רב ששת Rav
Sheshet was obviously a great great rabbi. ואמר רב נחמן אינך דיין
לעשות שודא דדייני. ve-amar Rav Nachman eincha dayan la-asot shuda de'dayanei. You
are not enough of an authority. So what תוספות Tosafot is saying
not that I trump you, it's that you fundamentally don't have the
qualifications to do שודא דדייני. shuda de'dayanei. So this is like the
flip side of תוספות's Tosafot approach of saying שודא דדייני shuda de'dayanei
is not just you figure it out to the best of your
ability, but you're empowered to make whatever decision you want. That idea
that I can make whatever arbitrary decision I want, that would only
be- there's only one one supreme judge other than God that gets
to do that, right? It has to be the greatest judge of
the generation. So that's- so you- you understand the two different ways
of reading this. One is רב נחמן Rav Nachman says maybe you
could but I am a bigger authority, I trump you, and what
תוספות is reading it is like no, שודא דדייני shuda de'dayanei is
not for any normal judge to make, שודא דדייני shuda de'dayanei is
only something that the big guys get to make.
Okay so- meaning really it even means it's, you know, based on
so much experience that he's instinctively probably going to be
right?
I don't know, yeah, or it's just a power thing, yeah, authority
thing, yeah.
Can you just imagine what משה Moshe was going through before he
handed over judgment?
There you go, exactly. So let's- the גמרא Gemara says like this:
Okay, so number one, I'm a judge and you're not. Number two,
that was only number one. ואו, ve-o, number two, מעיקרא לאו בתורת
הכי עשית לה. mei-ikara lav be-torat hachi asit lah. When you gave
it to רמי בר חמא, Rami Bar Chama, you didn't give it
in the capacity of שודא דדייני. shuda de'dayanei. You gave it to
רמי בר חמא Rami Bar Chama because you thought he really deserved-
like you thought that you were doing a normal judgment, that the
evidence was that he got it first and he deserved it. If
you want to do שודא דדייני, shuda de'dayanei, you have to be
exercising that power. You have to be consciously saying I am empowered
to award it to whomever I see fit and I'm awarding it
to X. That would be a שודא דדייני. shuda de'dayanei. That's not
what you did. You said he gets it because he- because his
document came first. That was a wrong judgment. We don't go by
who got the document first. We go by the dates in the
document. Okay, so that's what he's saying. You don't get to retroactively
make it a שודא דדייני. shuda de'dayanei. Okay.
But except the dates- but- but- he's on the right side of
that too. He has the document first.
He received it first, but the dates are the same dates. Like
they both say January first, one had it at 9:00 a.m. and
one had it at 4:00 p.m., but those hours weren't written in
the document.
You can't go by that. You have to go- you have to
exercise the judicial power and you're not a judge.
Right. Exactly.
But she did give it to
him first
and- right, so you got it first but that doesn't matter. He's
saying you got it first but we don't go by when- but
we don't go by when it was received, we go by the
dates written in the document.
So when he said I did שודא דדייני, shuda de'dayanei, you're saying
that afterwards
he's saying it's not really true? Yeah, when you did it, you
weren't doing שודא דדייני. shuda de'dayanei.
You only said I
did it be- No, he didn't say it at the time. Now
that his position- his פסק psak was being challenged, he said okay
fine, you think I ruled wrong? You think that the rule is
שודא דדייני? shuda de'dayanei? So say what I did was שודא דדייני.
shuda de'dayanei. And he said you can't say retroactively that it was
שודא דדייני. shuda de'dayanei. שודא דדייני shuda de'dayanei is a conscious use
of judicial power. Okay. It is not basically an attempt to adjudicate
and to say like this is actually what the law says. Okay.
This is what I- it's what I the judge am deciding, not
what the law says. All right. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: הנהו תרי שטרי, Hano Tray Shtari, let's get to the משנה.
That was the end of that. Now we have one more case.
הנהו תרי שטרי
דאתו.
Hano Tray
Shtari DeAsu.
Wait, so it ended by רב נחמן and he gave it to
the second one, to מר עוקבא? Mar Ukva?
Only because a judge can decide and he decided that.
Exactly. Exactly. And because the documents had the same date.
The situation is the power of the judge.
Exactly. And the other point to make in terms of the legal
point is that this seems to be using שודא דדייני Shuda DeDayni
even assuming like רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. That we go by, right
until now we've been saying שודא דדייני Shuda DeDayni when we go
by when it was given but we can't determine it. Now we're
saying you can even do שודא דדייני Shuda DeDayni even if you
go by the documents and they're both equally valid, well, you know,
exact same documents, and logically until now we've been saying יחלוקו, Yachloku,
two equal documents, there's no other evidence to be brought, it doesn't
matter who got it first, so divide it, and now we're actually
saying no, even in that case you could do שודא דדייני. Shuda
DeDayni.
This exercise of purely rabbinic authority.
Judicial, let's say power, yeah. Yeah, yeah. So now I mean except
that the judges are being given that power by the rabbis so
you could make it indirectly rabbinic authority, but yes. Okay, let's get
to the משנה.
In front of any, in both of these cases, the first one
and this one, it was the, the person who initiated the situation
did something that doesn't make sense.
Wait, so the בכור Bechor loses out?
It doesn't make sense. In other words, this mother did something.
Right, the person who's writing two identical documents or whatever is either
duping or something, right.
Does the second one have any leg to stand on to say
look, let's split this thing like we're talking about in the other
opinion because it was done this way, the intention was confused, if
not deceitful it was at least confused? They take this old woman
who,
right, yeah, I don't know. I mean the גמרא Gemara assumes like
that's part of why we're trying to figure out how to divide
it because we can't figure out what this person's intent was, but
it doesn't necessarily mean that the second intent was, maybe the person
all along was saying like רמי בר חמא Rami Bar Chama was
giving her such a hard time, please, please, please, fine I'll just
write him some fake document, I'm really going to give it to
the other one. So, you know, there's no way of knowing whether
it's the first or the second. Okay, right, let's get to the
משנה. Okay, גמרא says like this. Okay, הנהו תרי שטרי דאתו לקמיה
דרב יוסף,
Hano Tray Shtari DeAsu
Lekamei DeRav Yosef,
two documents were presented to רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. חד הוה כתיב
בחמשה בניסן, Chad Havei Kasiv BeChamsha BeNissan,
one said on the fifth of ניסן, Nissan, וחד הוה כתיב בניסן
סתם. VeChad Havei Kasiv BeNissan Stam.
So now basically that and the other said that it was given
over on ניסן Nissan and they accidentally
left out which day.
So אוקמי רב יוסף לההוא
דחמשה בניסן בנכסים,
Ukmi Rav Yosef LeHahu DeChamsha
BeNissan BeNechasim, he gave the field to the guy who it says
five in ניסן. Nissan. Because אמר ליה אידך, Amar Lei Idach, the
other said, ואנא אפסיד, VeAna Afsid, I'm going to lose out, I
really got it earlier. אמר ליה את ידך על התחתונה, Amar Lei
At Yadcha Al Hatachtona, no, your document is unclear. You have the
burden of proof or you're in the weaker position. אימא בעשרים ותשעה
בניסן את, Eima BeEsrim VeTishah BeNissan At,
maybe you were given it on the twenty-ninth of ניסן. Nissan. So
you can't prove, he has a very specific date and so even
though you know you own it, it's not like this case of,
so this is different than two of them on the same day,
one on an ambiguous day. So the person who's ambiguous is in
the weakest position. Okay, אמר ליה ונכתוב לי מר טירפא מאייר ואילך,
Amar Lei Venichtov Li Mar Tirfa MeIyar VeEilach,
fine,
but now, now let's get to sort of Michael's point about getting
your money back. Okay fine, so you're throwing out my document, but
I paid ten thousand dollars for the field, and now I'm not
being awarded the field, you're giving it to the other guy, let
me go collect my ten thousand, now the guy who sold me
the field is dead,
but he has other fields that other people own that I have
a lien on for reimbursement if for whatever reason I lost the
field he sold me. So I lost it, you awarded it to
the first guy, the five in ניסן Nissan guy, then they can't
say, wait, so I want to now get my money back, let
me now go to the people who bought other fields from this
guy and get it from them, and you're telling me that my
document, worst-case scenario, is dated the last day of ניסן, Nissan, so
I should have liens starting on day one of אייר, Iyar, and
let me go ahead and exercise those liens to get reimbursed.
Is that, whatever.
He says that's a reasonable request. אמר ליה יכלו למימר לך, Amar
Lei Yachlu Lemeimar Lach, no,
those people with the fields can tell you, את בר ניסן את,
At Bar Nissan
At, no, no, no, not go to the first one, they could
say, you don't have a right to exercise those liens, the guy
actually sold you the field on the first of ניסן, Nissan, and
that field is actually still yours. I don't care that the court
awarded it to the other guy. The reality is that that field
is still yours and you're not entitled to get reimbursed for it.
Now that's bizarre because you would think that if the court decided
to award it to the second guy, that created that as a
fact. I mean the first guy, they awarded it to the five
in ניסן Nissan guy, then they can't say well objectively speaking you
really did own the field. It doesn't matter, right now as a
fact of law it was given to the other guy, it was
determined as a matter of law that I don't own that field,
so I should be entitled to get my money back from you.
So that's a very bizarre that they can say to him oh
no we really think... You're the real owner so we're not going
to reimburse you. All right, so the גמרא says, "So מאי תקנתיה?
mai takante? So what can he do to get his money back?
So ניכתוב הרשאה להדדי. nichtov harsha'a l'adadei. They have to give each
other a power of attorney, meaning I go to Michael, whose שטר
said the five in ניסן, Nissan, I said, "Look Michael, we all
know that that field is mine, but they didn't have the right
date in that document. You won it, fine. But do me a
favor, Michael. Give me your power of attorney to collect reimbursement because
I'm going to go now to you and I'm going to say
I want that money back because my field was taken from me.
And you're going to say, "No, you owned the field, right? The
only person who can collect from me is Michael because it really
is your field, not Michael. Michael is the one that's entitled to
reimbursement." I say, "Oh, guess what? Michael made me power of attorney."
Okay? So therefore I'm going to collect from you. You either have
to reimburse me because it wound up being not my field, or
you have to reimburse Michael because it wound up not being your
field. So Michael at least will do me that favor to give
me power of attorney so one- I'm collecting for one of us
reimbursement but I'm going to pocket it as long as I'm not
getting the field." What's it got to do? It means if each-
it doesn't really mean להדדי, l'adadei, it really means you empower me.
Okay. All right, so with that we will end. תזכו למצוות. tizku
l'mitzvot. Go
out into the field. Exactly. Bum-bum-bum.